Guide to the Robert Klonsky Papers ALBA.219
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Robert Klonsky Papers
1937-1999
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Klonsky, Robert
ALBA.219
0.25 Linear Feet (1 box)
Robert Klonsky was born March 12, 1918 and grew up in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn, NY, in a garment worker's family of Russian Jewish descent. He sailed for Europe, traveling under the name Max Klonsky, on February 5, 1937 and arrived in Spain in time to fight with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Battle of Jarama in the same month. He later took part in the Battle of Brunete and, suffering ill health, left Spain in October 1937. After serving in World War II, he settled in Los Angeles, where he became active in the Communist Party of California and in many campaigns for peace and human rights. He died in Chicago in 2002. The collection includes typed transcripts of 23 letters and postcards written by Klonsky from Spain during the Spanish Civil War; they are addressed to various members of his family, including his older brother, Mac. Also included are World War II letters; clippings; a flyer for a James Connolly Commemoration at Jarama, 1937 (photocopy); a text of a speech by Klonsky in Leningrad, 1970s; an article about Klonsky by Floyce Alexander; documents relating to Klonsky's work in the Communist Party; testimony related to HUAC hearings; and Klonsky's speech at his subsequent trial under the Smith Act. Incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence, include a letter from Ray Bradbury, 1966, one from William O. Douglas, 1963, and drafts of a long letters from Klonsky to Henry Winston and Bettina Aptheker.
Scope and Contents
The collection includes typed transcripts of 23 letters and postcards written by Klonsky from Spain during the Spanish Civil War; they are addressed to various members of his family, including his older brother, Mac. Also included are World War II letters; clippings; a flyer for a James Connolly Commemoration at Jarama, 1937 (photocopy); a text of a speech by Klonsky in Leningrad, 1970s; an article on Klonsky by Floyce Alexander; documents relating to Klonsky's work in the Communist Party, incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence; testimony related to HUAC hearings; and Klonsky's speech at his subsequent trial under the Smith Act.
Arrangement
Files are organized in 1 series: I. General files, 1937-1999.
Folders are arranged alphabetically.
Historical/Biographical Note
Robert Klonsky was born March 12, 1918 and grew up in the Brownsville section of Brooklyn, NY, in a garment worker's family of Russian Jewish descent. He sailed for Europe, traveling under the name Max Klonsky, on February 5, 1937 and arrived in Spain in time to fight with the Abraham Lincoln Brigade in the Battle of Jarama in the same month. He later took part in the Battle of Brunete and, suffering ill health, left Spain in October 1937.
Klonsky served in World War II, where he saw action in Saipan and Okinawa, and after the War settled in Los Angeles, where he was active in the Communist Party of California and in many campaigns for peace, civil rights and human rights (especially in Latin America). For some years he ran a bookstore near the UCLA campus; the store was destroyed by arsonists, who painted swastikas on its wall. He worked closely with the Hollywood Ten and others who were subject to government investigation for "subversive" activity. In the 1950s he was tried under the Smith Act, was convicted of "conspiring to advocate Marxist views," and served time in prison. The case was eventually overturned by the Supreme Court. After forty years in California he moved to Santa Fe, NM. An article describing his experiences in Spain and his later political activity, "Alma sin Fronteras" (Soul without Frontiers) by Floyce Alexander, appeared in the Albuquerque (NM) Journal on May 12, 1987. The article includes a dramatic account of the death in Spain of his friend, Boston volunteer John Lenthier. Robert Klonsky died in Chicago on September 7, 2002.
Access Restrictions
Materials are open to researchers. Please contact the Tamiment Library & Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives for more information and to schedule an appointment, tamiment.wagner@nyu.edu or 212-998-2630.
Related Archival Material
ALBA collections at the Tamiment Library.
Provenance
The Klonsky Papers came to the Tamiment Library as part of the original acquisition of ALBA collections, formerly at Brandeis University, in 2001.
Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans -- United States -- Correspondence.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Participation, American; Communist Party of the United States of America (Calif.); Spain. Ejército Popular de la República. Abraham Lincoln Battalion; Klonsky, Robert
- Series I: General Files, 1937-1999.
  Scope and Content Note
  The collection includes typed transcripts of 23 letters and postcards written by Klonsky from Spain during the Spanish Civil War; they are addressed to various members of his family, including his older brother, Mac. Also included are World War II letters; clippings; a flyer for a James Connolly Commemoration at Jarama, 1937 (photocopy); a text of a speech by Klonsky in Leningrad, 1970s; an article about Klonsky by Floyce Alexander; documents relating to Klonsky's work in the Communist Party, incoming and copies of outgoing correspondence, including a letter from Ray Bradbury, 1966, one from William O. Douglas, 1963, and a draft of long letters from Klonsky to Henry Winston and Bettina Aptheker; testimony related to HUAC hearings; and Klonsky's speech at his subsequent trial under the Smith Act.
  - Agent's Report, to Commissioner Reimer re: "Welcome Home" Meeting Featuring RK and David McKelvy White, [Feb 1938?] (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Alexander, Floyce, "'Soul without Frontiers': A Veteran of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade Offers President Reagan a History Lesson" (typescript, article about RK), [1980s] (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Anonymous Note, to Chairman, UCLA English Department (re: RK a Communist), 1958 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Aptheker, Bettina, from RK (carbon, p. 1 missing), [Aug 14, 1975] (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Bradbury, Ray, to RK, [ca. 1966] (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Clipping on Sentencing of Nine Local Communists, including RK (Philadelphia Evening Bulletin), 1955 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Commemoration Program for the Easter Rising of 1916 in Spain (copy, with mention of E. Flaherty, P. O'Connor, M. Hourihan, Gilmore, RK, and others), 1937 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - [Diskin], Lou, from RK (carbon), Aug 13, 1975; Klonsky, Robert (Box 1, Folder 8)
    Communism -- California.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Veterans -- United States -- Correspondence.; Communism and art -- United States.; Spain -- History -- Civil War, 1936-1939 -- Personal narratives, American.; Klonsky, Robert; Communist Party of the United States of America (Calif.)
  - Douglas, William O., to RK, 1963 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fishman, Moe, to RK, 1985 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Hadwin, Tom (British IB volunteer), to RK, Dec 14, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Hall, Charles (Chicago Friends of the Lincoln Brigade), to RK, 1999 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - HUAC: Subpoena, RK to Appear before the Committee on Un-American Activities (HUAC), Los Angeles, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - "Jungle Journal Supplement," Poetry (typescript, 3 pp, unsigned), Undated (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Lenin Memorial Mass Meeting, Philadelphia (flyer, featuring H. Winston, J. Stachel, P. Bart), [1936?] (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Lowenfels, Walter: Poem, on a Spanish Civil War Volunteer, Mar 12, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - National United Committee to Free Angela Davis and All Political Prisoners, 1971 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Pre-Sentencing Speech, RK, Sep 1954 (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Sartre, Jean-Paul, to RK, 1965 (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Spanish Civil War Letters: RK to His Family, Feb-Mar 1937 (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Spanish Civil War Letters: RK to His Family, Apr 1937 (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Spanish Civil War Letters: RK to His Family, May-Jun 1937 (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Statement: RK to Leningrad Peace Conference, [1977?] (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Tenants Rights Flyer, Communist Party of Eastern Pennsylvania, 1947 (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Veterans of the Abraham Lincoln Brigade, from RK (on Angela Davis, etc.), 1972 (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Winston, Henry, from RK (lengthy draft commentary on problems of the California Communist Party, "the Healeys," etc.), Undated (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - World War II Letter: RK to Mac Klonsky, Jan 8, 1946 (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - World War II Letter: RK to "Mom and Pop" (on Passover), Mar 26, 1945 (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - World War II Memorabilia: Pay Book, Discharge Card, and Photograph (RK?), 1945-1946, undated (Box 1, Folder 29)